[MUSIC]
Today, I'm going to talk
about the fragment class.
Fragments were added to Android in version
3.0 to better support user interfaces for
de, devices with large screens,
such as tablets.
Now, over the last few years,
the popularity of tablets
has grown incredibly.
And as I'm sure you know, tablets have
larger displays than phones typically do.
So, because of these larger screens,
some of the design heuristics that made
sense for a smaller phone display,
no longer work.
In particular, we can comfortably do
much more on a large tablet display,
than we could do on a small phone display.
Now, to put this in concrete terms,
let's take a look at a simple
application called QuoteViewer.
QuoteViewer is an application
comprised of two activities.
The first activity shows the titles
of several Shakespeare plays and
allows the user to select
one title at a time.
And when the user selects that title, a
second activity is started which displays
one quote from that play,
let's take a look.
Now I'll launch the QuoteViewer
application, the first activity starts up.
And shows us the titles of three
Shakespeare plays, Hamlet, King Lear, and
Julius Ceasar.
Let me click on Hamlet.
This starts the second
activity which shows me
Horatio's quote as Hamlet is dying.
Now cracks a noble heart.
Good night sweet prince, and
flights of angels sing thee to thy rest.
Now I'll hit the Back button
to return to the titles.
And next, I'll click on King Lear.
And again, we get a quote, this time,
one from the blinded Earl of Gloucester
who says, as flies to wanton boys, are we
to the gods, they kill us for their sport.
And once again, I hit the Back
button to return to the titles.
And this time I click on Julius Ceasar.
And again, the second activity
starts up and we see a quote.
This one, where Brutus urges
Cassius to go on the attack.
He says, there is a tide in the affairs
of men, which taken at the flood,
leads on to fortune.
Omitted, all the voyage of their life
is bound in shallows and in miseries.
Now this is a fine interface for a phone.
In fact, it would be hard to do much
else and still have a readable and
easy to use interface.
On a tablet, however,
this same layout is pretty lame.
Now here, let me show you.
Here I'm showing an emulated tablet.
I'll click on the Launcher icon.
And now I'll start the QuoteViewer
application we just saw, on the phone.
And the first thing you notice
is all that unused white space.
The titles take up just a little space
on the left side of the display, and
the rest is pretty much wasted.
Now let me click on Hamlet.
And here you see that the quote stretches
all the way across the ten inch tablet but
uses little of the vertical space.
Now I'll hit the Back button
to go back to the titles.
And I can do the same thing for
the King Lear quote.
And the same thing for
the Julius Caesar quote.
And besides not being,
not using the available space too well,
this layout imposes a slow back and
forth navigation style where the user
has to keep moving their hand from
the title then down to the back button,
then back to the title and so on.
So, let's see a better layout that
uses both or shows both the titles and
the quotes at the same time.
I'll click on the Launcher icon and
then start up the fragment
static layout application.
And this initially brings up a user
interface that looks exactly like what you
saw with the QuoteViewer application.
However, when I click on the title,
Hamlet, you see that the user interface
gets essentially divided into two parts.
The titles stay where they
were on the left, but
the quote is now shown simultaneously
on the right side of the screen.
And now if I want to
see a different quote,
I simply select a new
play title on the left.
Here I'll select King Lear.
And again, the quote pops up on the right.
And the same thing when
I select Julius Caesar.
Now overall,
this layout works much better on
a tablet than QuoteViewer's layout does.
In particular, it avoids wasted space, and
it makes navigation a little bit
easier because I don't have to
keep moving my hands down to the bottom
of the display to hit the Back button.
And then up to the titles, and so on.
The QuoteViewer application
was made up of two activities.
The fragment static layout
application that we just saw,
however, is made up of a single activity.
That single activity,
however, hosts two fragments.
Fragments represent the portion
of an activity's user interface.
The fragment static layout application,
for
example, has two such interface portions.
One for the titles goes on the left and
one for the quotes that goes on the right.
And each of these portions of the user
interface is implemented as a fragment.
Fragments are hosted by activities.
One activity can host zero or
more fragments.
And one fragment can be used
across zero or more activities.
Now as I said,
fragments are hosted by activities.
So fragments have to be
loaded into the activity and
then displayed, removed, and so
on as the activity changes its state.
And as a result the lifecycle
of a fragment is tied to and
coordinated with the lifecycle of
the activity that's hosting it.
At the same time however, fragments have
some of their own life cycle call backs.
For now,
let's talk about the fragment life cycle,
assuming that the fragment is statically
bound to its hosting activity.
We'll talk about dynamically adding and
removing fragments from a hosting
activity a little bit later.
So, a fragment can be in a running or
resumed state.
And when it's in this state, the fragment
is visible in the running activity.
A fragment can also be
in a paused state and
fragments will be paused when their
hosting activity is visible but
some other activity is in
the foreground and has focus.
A fragment can also be in a stopped state.
In this state,
the fragment is not visible.
Let's talk now about the life
cycle callback methods
that a fragment can receive.
And we'll talk about when those
methods might be called relative to
the life cycle states of the activity
that hosts the fragment.
When a fragment's hosting
activity is being created,
the fragment may receive several
life cycle method calls.
First, when a fragment is
attached to its hosting activity,
the fragment receives a call to onAttach.
Next, the fragment receives
a call to its onCreate method.
And note here that I'm referring to
the fragment.onCreate method, not
the activity.onCreate method that we've
talked so much about in previous lessons.
And as with the actitity.onCreate method,
you typically initialize the fragment
in the fragment's onCreate method,
one difference between the two
method however, is that unlike in
activity.onCreate you don't set up
the user interface in fragment.onCreate.
That actually happens in the next method.
Now, after onCreate, Android calls
the fragments onCreateView method.
And this method sets up and returns a view
containing the fragment's user interface.
And this view is then given
to the hosting activity so
it can install that view in
the activity's view hierarchy.
And finally, after the hosting
activity has been created and
the fragment's user interface
has been installed,
then the fragment receives a call
to it's onActivityCreated method.
Now, while the fragment is
attached to the hosting activity,
It's life'cycle is dependent
on it's hosts life cycle.
For example, if the hosting activity
is about to become visible,
it will receive a call
from its onStart method.
The fragment therefore will also
receive a call to its onStart method.
When the hosting activity is about
to become visible and ready for
user interaction Android calls
the fragments onResume method.
And when the hosting activity is visible
but another activity is about to
come into the foreground, Android
calls the fragment's onPause method.
And when the hosting activity is no
longer visible the fragment
receives a call to onStop.
Now, when he hosting activity is about
to be destroyed any fragments that
it's hosting also have to be shut down.
And, this happens in several steps.
First, when the fragments
user interface view,
the one that was previously created by the
call to onCreateView, when that view has
been detached from the activity, the
fragment receives a call to onDestroyView.
And here you can do things like clean
up resources associated with the view.
Next, when the fragment
is no longer in use,
it receives a call to
it's onDestroy method.
And here you can do things like
release fragment resources.
Next, when the fragment is no longer
attached to its hosting activity,
it will receive a call to onDetach.
And here you might do things like
null out references to the fragment's
hosting activity.